This video is sponsored by Saley. Get
affordable internet connection wherever
you travel without roaming fees. Get an
exclusive 15% discount on Saley plans
through the link in the description and
use code wonder15 at checkout.
The following is an allegorical
interpretation of a thought experiment
posed by 17th century philosopher Blaise
Pascal, which reveals something
simultaneously profound and deeply
unsettling about the modern world.
Every week a man goes to a race course
to gamble on horse racing. His hope is
to eventually win a large enough sum of
money that will change his life.
After years and years of this without
having achieved anything near his goal,
the man has now become a regular at the
course, known by all the aristocrats,
merchants, stewards, bookmakers, and so
on who frequent or work the course.
One aristocrat in particular who
regularly visits the race course out of
a love for the art of [music] horse
racing often observes the gambling man's
constant and obsessive betting. He
watches him lose over and over only
occasionally winning. He watches him
thrash with agitation as the horse races
take place.
One day the aristocrat approaches the
gambling man. "How much money are you
hoping to ultimately win?" he asks.
"What would satisfy you?"
The gambling man pauses for a moment,
confused. Then he murmurs the number to
the aristocrat. "Hmm," says the
aristocrat. He reaches into his
waistcoat pocket and pulls out a large
sack of coins. "Here,
there is your money." the aristocrat
continues.
The gambling man stares down at the
coins, his eyes widening and lighting
up. "But," continues the aristocrat,
"you can never gamble here again. Okay?
In fact, you can never gamble anywhere.
I know of every race course, tavern,
[music] inn, house, club. None of them."
"Why?" asks the gambling man. "Firstly,
you're missing out on the beauty of
these races and games. Secondly, if you
gamble again, you will surely lose my
money. And my money does not go to
waste."
Dumbfounded but elated, the gambling man
agrees.
Several weeks go by and the gambling man
can no longer take it. He is miserable.
He got what he was gambling for, but
something is missing.
Soon he returns to the race course,
approaches the bookmaker's counter, and
asks to place a bet.
"I can't." says the bookmaker. "You
agreed to the aristocrat's terms. I
cannot participate in breaking them."
"Please." says the gambling man.
"You can play, but you can't bet actual
money. And I can't let you win." the
bookmaker responds.
Desperate to do something, to play
again, the gambling man agrees.
Every week he returns to the race course
and places fake bets, knowing full well
that he will not win anything. He
watches the horses whip by on the course
and feels nothing.
There's no hope, no uncertainty.
On the verge of complete and utter
despair, the gambling man decides he
must undo what he's done.
He returns to the aristocrat.
"Here." says the gambling man.
"What is this?" asks the aristocrat.
"It's the money I still have. Nearly all
of it you gave me. I don't agree to the
terms anymore.
I'm going to gamble again."
"Why?"
"Isn't this money what you were after?"
"I guess not."
says the gambling man.
In Pascal's book Pensées, he uses this
thought experiment to explore what he
believed to be humanity's greatest
plight, boredom. For him, most human
activity is a result of a kind of
existential boredom. More specifically,
the result of our intense repulsion of
boredom.
>> [music]
>> Boredom creates space for us to think
and feel fully and without distraction.
It allows us to see and know the
wretchedness of our condition. According
to Pascal, we loathe this experience. We
refuse to confront the realities of our
being. And so we agitatedly do and
pursue things,
>> [music]
>> creating distractions and problems to
occupy ourselves away from ourselves.
Pascal writes, "All of humanity's
problems stem from man's inability to
sit quietly in a room alone." [music]
As a result of this, for Pascal, it's
rarely the outcome of our endeavors that
we are truly after. As illustrated with
the gambling man, we don't really want
the outcome to materialize fully. This
would destroy the point. Rather, what we
really want is to occupy ourselves
>> [music]
>> in the service of obtaining some outcome
that is possible but uncertain. It's the
continued potential for obtaining
something and the belief that obtaining
it will benefit or satisfy [music] us
that keeps us satisfied.
In plain terms, we gamble or do things
that fit this gambling pattern
>> [music]
>> because we are trying to continually
escape ourselves, our boredom and our
awareness of our condition.
In the words of Dostoevsky in The
Gambler,
"Gamblers know a man can sit for almost
24 hours at cards without looking to
right or to [music] left."
Gambling away the modern world.
Gambling has never been more popular
than it is today. It's estimated that
around 1.6 billion people worldwide
gamble regularly and over 4 billion
people gamble at least once every year.
That's over 50% of the global
population. This increase has seen its
biggest ramp in the last 30 or so years
with both the internet and smartphones
creating unprecedented accessibility.
Among many other things, we now indulge
in our impulse toward escapism [music]
through gambling and media at obscene
scales. More than just the increase in
popularity of traditional gambling like
casino games, sports betting, and so on,
as a culture, [music] we've also
recently begun to make gambling markets
out of everything.
On what are known as prediction market
platforms, you can gamble on essentially
anything that is uncertain in the world.
Will Jesus Christ return by 2027? You
can bet on it. How many starving
children are there in a particular war
zone? You can bet on it. Will a nuclear
weapon detonate by June of this year?
Will a political figure wear a certain
color tie or name a country a certain
number of times in a speech?
You can bet on it. Will some influencer
do some influencer thing? You get the
idea. Interestingly, prediction markets
actually originated for utilitarian
purposes. Launching in 1988 at the
University of Iowa, researchers used
experimental prediction markets to try
to determine the accuracy in foreseeing
political events when individuals were
financially incentivized to predict
correctly. The goal was essentially to
determine what we could learn about the
world when we let people bet on things.
When human predictions are decoupled
from biased desires or preferences for
the outcome. The study did in fact find
that these markets often do produce more
accurate predictions than traditional
methods. However, what we also learned
since then is if you let people bet on
things, they'll bet on everything.
The nihilism loop.
What does it suggest about humanity's
current relationship with itself
>> [music]
>> when, despite the vast increase in the
availability of interests, knowledge,
things to do, and places to explore, we
have dramatically increased the amount
of gambling we do on trivial games and
bets? [music]
Of course, gambling can be fun for fun's
sake. Like anything else, it can be done
without having broader or deeper
implications. In its most basic form,
there is arguably nothing inherently
wrong with gambling. In fact, one could
easily argue that nearly everything we
do in life [music] is a kind of gamble.
But it is perhaps emblematic of
something deeper when the level of
habitual, trivial, casino-like gambling
rises to the immense cultural scales
[music] we are currently seeing.
There seems to be a kind of negativistic
feedback loop fueled by our unaddressed
existential boredom that is further
facilitated and augmented [music]
by modern technology.
This loop works as follows.
To avoid the discomfort of boredom, we
engage in activities and endeavors. We
direct our attention away from ourselves
and toward things as a misguided attempt
to resolve our condition externally.
When these things inevitably do not
resolve the underlying tension and
disquiet that we are trying to escape,
we become bored and agitated again.
Still unwilling to face boredom head-on,
we create new things and technologies
and start the loop over, trying to find
more forms of distraction.
Over time, these distractions seem to
become increasingly trivial and mundane
as the looping, gyrating nature of the
phenomenon seems to whittle down our
activities to increasing
meaninglessness.
We become more and more numb as both our
tolerance to distraction and sensitivity
to boredom increase. What we seem to
have arrived at is a place of such
cultural numbness that, rather than
reconcile our relationship with
ourselves and the events of the world,
we have turned everything into a kind of
game or spectacle.
>> [music]
>> This phenomenon, exemplified by
prediction markets, the proliferation of
gambling, as well as things like the
commodification and spectacularization
of the news and media, creates a dynamic
where we can engage with the world. We
can know and see what happens, but we
don't have to really hold any feelings
about it. At least not deeply [music]
and not for very long.
It's merely a bet, a clip, or a headline
that we can scroll past or quickly move
on from.
Author and theorist Neil Postman writes
in Amusing Ourselves to Death,
"When a population becomes distracted by
trivia, when cultural life is redefined
as a perpetual round of entertainments,
[music]
when serious public conversations
becomes a form of baby talk, when, in
short, a people become an audience and
their public business a vaudeville
[music] act, then a nation finds itself
at risk. Culture death is a clear
possibility."
Financial nihilism. [music]
There's also an obvious economic
component to our increasing cultural
nihilism and gambling [music]
proclivities, a kind of financial
nihilism.
In many countries today, wealth
inequality is at or near all-time
historic highs. We've all heard the
numbers. The top 10% of Americans own
about 70% of the nation's [music] wealth
and the top 1% own roughly 30%.
This wealth disparity, combined with the
rising prices for basic goods and a
seemingly perpetual sense of job,
technological, and global uncertainty,
>> [music]
>> can cause individuals to easily and
understandably feel as though they've
been left out from a shared sense of
growth and opportunity. [music]
When individuals feel disconnected from
the cultural narrative and system
they're a part of,
>> [music]
>> they naturally stop believing in it. At
least not fully.
One sees it as something unworthy of
investing much [music] time, effort, and
sincerity into and instead everything is
perceived through a kind of cynicism or
ironic detachment.
If it seems as unlikely to grow within a
system as it is to beat the odds in a
random chance bet, [music] what is
likely to emerge at scale?
What else is there to do but bet on
Jesus and [music] war?
To hope that the chaotic arbitrariness
that seems to have conspired against you
might randomly pluck you back up out
from the margins
and bring you into something.
Something is always missing.
Even in the best of cases, what we see
from the winner's circle of the modern
world's casino is mostly only the bright
neon lights of more casino games.
After a certain point,
>> [music]
>> winning doesn't do anything. The prize
money doesn't satisfy.
The gambling man in Pascal's thought
experiment shows us [music] this.
It is not winning, it is not losing. It
is the hope and uncertainty we
experience [music] in the games we
choose to play.
And so, what seems to matter is this.
Wisely choosing what games we play and
how.
Each of us have a choice in whether we
keep playing games or not. And each of
us have a choice in what kind of games
we play and what bets we place.
Can I fail to understand that I'm a lost
man, but can I not rise again?
Yes, all it would take is just once in
my life to be careful and patient. And
that's all there is to it.
All it would take is to stand firm just
once and I can change my whole destiny
in a single hour,
wrote Dostoevsky.
Rather than the increasingly easy and
accessible indulgences of trivial
things,
>> [music]
>> perhaps the true gamble in life is
betting on something hard, something
sincere,
something that one truly cares about
despite odds and despite the system in
which one exists.
This requires sitting with boredom. It
requires understanding more about what
it is that we are always trying to
escape or cover up. It requires
self-knowledge and the embrace of our
condition.
Through which, hopefully, eventually,
we find what matters to us deep down.
And through this,
this sincerity and depth,
perhaps we win
the great wager of life,
even if
we ultimately lose.
Whatever games we choose to play and
whatever bets we choose to place in
life, if we're lucky, we'll find
ourselves able to explore the world and
travel to different countries. Of
course, in the modern world, staying
connected to friends, family, work, and
our interests, wherever we are, [music]
is simultaneously essential as well as
expensive and convoluted. This video's
sponsor, Saley, a new eSIM service app,
solves all of this and makes staying
connected simple and convenient. I'm
hoping to do some international
traveling myself coming up this summer,
but doing so requires that I still have
the ability to maintain connection with
my work. This means I'll need data on my
phone. However, I loathe dealing with
trying to obtain a local SIM card at the
airport and getting them from random
stores or vendors can put you at risk of
scams. Saley, however, allows me to
download the app once at home, install
the eSIM, prepay and preplan, and I'm
done. Just a couple minutes of prep and
it will activate instantly [music] after
I land. This gives you full access to
the internet in over 200 countries
without exorbitant roaming fees
>> [music]
>> and without having to search for Wi-Fi
in unknown places. Not only can you
maintain connection easily and
affordably, but with Saley's security
features, you can also browse more
securely, change your virtual location,
block malicious ads, and stay safer with
web protection. All Saley eSIM plans are
compatible with iOS and Android devices
and if there's any reason your device is
not compatible, Saley will provide you
with the full refund. So, there's no
risk in trying it. If you're traveling
abroad soon or plan to in the future,
download Saley now and get an exclusive
15% discount on all Saley data plans
through the link in the description and
then use code wonder15 at checkout.
And of course, as always, thank you so
much for watching in general
and see you next video.